PROFESSOR: All right.
So in order to make this depth limited
search work, when we decide we've gone
as deeply as we can, and we're faced
with a state which is not a terminal
state, we need to have the ability
to decide is it good or bad.
So what we have is an
evaluation function.
What an evaluation function is, is a
function which takes a non-terminal
state, and returns some number.
Now we know we want out of this number,
just like we knew what we want
it out of a heuristic
and A-star search.
In this case, we want the number to
return the actual minimax value of
that position.
Now that's not going to happen.
Right?
That's the problem that's too hard
to solve in the first place.
In practice, what people do is they
try to come up with some function
which, on average, is positive when
the minimax value is positive.
It's negative when the minimax
value is negative.
It is in the ballpark to the extent
that that's possible.
So you look at this case.
Here's a check tree.
A very small piece of a chess tree.
And you might have the root.
Right?
And so here's at the root.
And at the root, you could just apply
your evaluation function.
You don't even need to do minimax.
You could just do a one step look ahead,
and then apply your evaluation
function and just be greedy and hill
climb your evaluation function.
In general, that's going
to be very bad.
Even if your evaluation function is
decent, you gain so much power by
embedding it in a minimax tree.
Here's another position.
This position might apply the same
evaluation function, but
deeper in the tree.
So as long as the evaluation function's
in the ballpark, it's much
safer to apply it down here.
Now what are these evaluation
functions?
Well in the case of chess, we might
say well there are some properties
that are important.
Like if white has more queens than
black, that's probably a
good sign for white.
If white has more knights than black,
that's a good sign for white.
But maybe not quite as important.
We might encapsulate some
notion of board control.
We might have to consult with chess
experts to figure out what these
features should be.
But what we do is we come up with
a bunch of features, which are
themselves functions which look at the
state and return some indicator.
So what we would have then
is a bunch of features.
Maybe queen advantage, knight advantage,
a bunch of things.
And then some measure
of board control.
Now each of them contributes.
And the typical thing to do is
combine them in a linear way.
More complicated things are
absolutely possible.
There are some nice properties you get
when you combine them linearly, which
we'll see later in the course.
So we might say, the queen advantage
is more important.
It gets a coefficient of 10, whereas
the knight advantage only gets a
coefficient of three.
And maybe board control
is really important.
And maybe that gets a
coefficient of 20.
So let's figure out what this
actually looks like.
An evaluation function takes the state
and returns a number that represents
the minimax value.
For something like PAC-MAN strictly
speaking it should be a score.
Right?
Because that's what you would compute if
you actually looked at the minimax
value of the game.
The terminal utilities are
marked the scores.
So let's think about something
like this.
You look at this and you think, what's
the minimax value of that?
Well I mean, I don't know.
I'll eat a bunch of those dots, right.
It doesn't look particularly
good or bad.
What about this?
Is it better or worse?
Yeah, it looks worse.
Now it may turn out that in fact it's
not worse because over here, the ghost
may yet blank you.
Here they're basically been
reduced to one ghost.
These are the ways in which it's
a little bit subtle, right?
But at least on the surface, this
looks a little worse because the
ghosts are closer.
OK, how about this?
Better or worse?
Looks worse.
There's a couple reasons why you
might say this is worst.
One is that the dots have been eaten.
All right.
So there's fewer points left to get.
So depending on how you
deal with the score.
Also you're kind of getting towards dead
ends, and that's a little scary
when there are ghosts on your tail.
How about this?
Presumably our function should
return that this is bad.
How about this?
Also bad.
OK.
So let's see what happens when you
do evaluation functions in
the context of PAC-MAN.
So first, let's take a look
at a simple board.
There aren't even any ghosts.
So you think this should be easy.
I'm going to do something
like a depth two search.
And no ghosts are going to get
in my way, and I'm going
to win really easily.
So let's think about what PAC-MAN does
here in the case where you do a depth
two search.
And we need to truncation function.
So what's the truncation function?
Let's just use the score.
Right?
That's a pretty good indicator.
If the score is high, that's good.
If the score is bad, that's less good.
And so we're going to try to
kind of maximize our score.
Not purely greedily, but based
on a 2-step look ahead.
So here we go.
Here's the first step we take.
So far so good.
And then--
OK.
And you're starting to
doubt the agent here.
Somehow, even though we've got a
basically plausible evaluation
function, the score, and we're doing a
little bit of look ahead, he's just
wigging out.
What's going on here?
OK.
So what is going on here?
Let's take a look.
Why does PAC-MAN starve?
OK.
Well this is actually a danger
of replanting agents.
All of these agents that you're seeing
here that do depth limited search,
they do that search.
They take a move, and then they do the
search again from the next position.
Right?
That means the plan they have in their
head doesn't really have to be
consistent.
Right?
It's just at every step,
you do a new plan.
So let's take a look about what this
search tree looks like where PAC-MAN
has, say, two dots to eat.
Well, what can we do?
Well, intuitively, you look at it
and you're like, eat the dot.
Right?
But he's actually got two choices.
He could eat the dot, or you
can head off to the right.
Well, eating the dot is actually
better for the score right now.
So if we marked these with their current
score, and we just went off of
that, we would actually
go eat the dot.
But remember, there's more of
a look ahead than that.
What can you do from the left tree?
You could kind of go back.
So you're in the position of being kind
of in the middle of the board and
having eaten a dot.
What can you do from the right tree?
Well you can go left, which will put
you back where you started, and you
haven't eaten any dots.
You could go right and
you can eat a dot.
So you've got two futures here.
What will minimax do?
It's not really much of
a minimax, right?
Because there's no min.
But we can write down the points.
So if you get 10 points for a dot,
then here we'll have 10 points.
And zero points and 10 points.
So if we run minimax, we'll see all
right, this will be 10, this will be
10, the root will be 10.
So from the root, you look and you say,
east, west, it's all the same.
Because in two steps, under optimal
play, I'm going to get 10 points
either way.
And so there's no reason for PAC-MAN in
two steps to eat the dot and then
come back when it could just as
easily go for the other dot.
So what's wrong with that?
Well the problem is if we take this
branch, look at that state.
It's just like the state at the root.
And it's just as good from that state
to go left as to go right.
So we thrash.
What's the problem?
Everybody agrees that this
state here is bad.
Right?
But let's look at these other states.
Let's look at here is A and here's B.
The score says these are equally good.
But are they?
Are they really equally good?
In both cases we've eaten a dot.
But which one's better, A or B?
A is better.
Why is A better?
We're closer to the next dot.
So this is why the score function here,
it is an evaluation function,
but it can be improved.
And so if what we had is-- we could
maybe get some partial credit.
Like maybe we can get a point for having
been a little bit closer to
that next dot.
Well now A will look better.
And now with the root, this will be
11, this will be 11, and now we're
going to go for the close dot.
And it's not a tie.
Right?
There is a better sequence now.
So let's see what that does.
So here's that same configuration.
Still looking ahead, too.
But now the truncation
function is score.
But you get increasing credit
for being closer to a dot.
So now we take the same first step.
But now we go straight to the
end and don't thrash.
Many of you will see thrashing
in your projects.
When you see thrashing, it is usually
not a bug in minimax.
It's usually a deficiency in
your evaluation function.
All right.
So back to this case of evaluation
for PAC-MAN.
What about when it is adversarial?
Well you'll get a chance to play
with this kind of evaluation
function for the agent.
So what I'm going to show you is I'm
going to show you the flip side.
I'm going to show you the evaluation
function for the ghosts.
Now these ghosts may have a kind of deer
in the headlights look in their
eyes, but they are in fact
now running minimax.
They are adversarial.
And they have an evaluation function.
Let's think about it for a second.
They don't get points for eating
dots or anything like that.
They're not trying to
get close to dots.
What they're trying to do is they're
trying to defeat PAC-MAN.
So they've got things like,
am I getting close?
At the end, of course, they can
see the game actually end.
And if they get within a horizon where
they can see the end of the game,
they're going to take the appropriate
tactical action to bring it about.
So let's take a look and
see what they do.
You will have seen before the ghosts
kind of milling about and wandering
kind of randomly.
These are mastermind ghosts,
so let's take a look.
Slower because every agent
has to do this stuff.
And oh.
Let's see it again.
So watch.
They generally move towards
PAC-MAN, largely based on
the evaluation function.
And at the end they can see what's going
to happen, and they take some
fancy tactical action, not because
of the evaluation function.
But because minimax can see how they
have to move in order to successfully
pin PAC-MAN.
Let's zoom in.
Sometimes I feel bad for PAC-MAN.
OK.
So the question is what's
going on here?
And there's actually two agents here.
They are separately doing
their own searches.
But when they see a node that the other
one controls, they treat it like
a min node.
So even though each agent is actually
doing its own search, because they are
both assuming the other one shares its
evaluation function, that is, is also
a minimizing agent, we're going
to see cooperation emerge.
So this is really pure two player
minimax in the sense that there are
actually two minimizing agents.
What's cool about is this shows you how
you can get cooperation without
programming it in.
Simply because they're both trying to
achieve the same goal, as soon as the
orange agent goes in one direction, the
blue agent will compute and see
that the way you can force PAC-MAN to
lose is by going the other direction.
And so they're going to flank.
OK.
One more time.
This is not program behavior.
This is a consequence of minimax.
Right?
Minimax does tactical
things very well.
The evaluation function generally
determines your strategy.
So here's that flanking tactic again.
They split up.
It's not a joint decision.
It's just they both know that they're
trying to achieve the same thing.